在接下来的三部分里，我们稍微改变一下讨论内容
In the next three segments we will change
gears a little bit and talk about the
来讨论一下PRG的定义。这个定义真的是一种很好的理解PRG的方式
definition of a PRG. This definition is a
really good way to think of a PRG. And we
will see many applications for this
definition. So consider a PRG with
并且我们能看到这个定义的很多应用。那么令PRG有
keyspace K that ouputs N bit strings. Our
goal is to define, what does it mean for
秘钥空间K，输出N比特序列。我们的目标是定义
the output of the generator to be
indistinguishable from random? In other
无法与随机序列区分生成器的输出是什么？
words, we're gonna define a distribution
that basically is defined by choosing a
换句话说，我们要定义一个分布
random key in the keyspace. Remember that
a arrow with R above it means choosing
从秘钥空间里随机选取秘钥。记住上面那个带R的箭头意味着
uniformly from the set script K. And then
we output, basically, the output of the
从集合K中随机地选取，然后我们用这个生成器的输出。
generator. And what we'd like to say. Is
that this distribution. This distribution
并且我们所说的就是这个分布
of pseudo random strings is
indistinguishable from a truly uniform
这个伪随机序列分布和真正的均匀分布没有区别
换句话说，如果我们仅选择一个真正均匀的0，1
distribution. In other words, if we just
choose a truly uniform string in 01 to the
N位序列并且输出这个序列，我们说这两个分布
N and simply output this string, we'd like
to say that these two distributions are
没有区别。如果大家现在想想，这真的
indistinguishable from one another. Now if
you think about it, this sounds really
很令人吃惊，因为如果我们画一个圈表示所有n位01序列，
surprising because if we draw a circle
here of all possible strings in 01 to the
那么均匀分布能够等概输出这些序列
N, then the uniform distribution basically
can ouput any of these strings with equal
这就是均匀分布的定义。然而
probability. That's the definition of the
uniform distribution. However a
这个生成器G生成的伪随机分布，由于种子空间
pseudo-random distribution generated by
this generator G. Because the seed space
很小，可能输出的集合是非常小的
is so small, the set of possible outputs
is really, really small, it's tiny inside
是N位01序列集合中很小的子集。这就是这个生成器能输出的全部。然而
of, 01 to the N. And this is really all
that the generator can output. And yet,
我们讨论，敌手看到生成器的输出的
what we're arguing is that an adversary
who looks at the output of the generator
小集合的元素，无法区分它和均匀分布输出的
in this tiny set can't distinguish it from
the output of the uniform distribution
整个集合的元素，我想这就是我们真正想要的性质
over the entire set. I think that's the
property that we're actually shooting for.
因此要理解怎么定义这个无法和随机区分的概念
So to understand how to define this
concept of indistinguishability from
我们需要统计测试的概念。因此让我来定义一下
random, we need the concept of a
statistical test. So, let me define what a
N位01序列的统计测试是什么。我会用字母A来表示这些统计测试
statistical test on 01 to the N is. I'm
gonna define these statistical tests by
统计测试是一个算法，用
the letter A. And the statistical test is
basically an algorithm that takes its
N比特序列的输入，输出0或1。现在我告诉大家
inputs and N bit string, and simply
outputs zero or one. Now I'll tell you
0，我们认为它是统计测试说
that zero, we're gonna think of it as
though the statistical test said, the
你的输入不是随机的。1，我们把它想成统计测试说
input you gave me is not random. And one,
we're going to think of it as saying that
你的输入是随机的。好，统计测试所做的是
the imput you gave me actually is random.
Okay, so all this statistical test does is
用给它的输入n比特序列x
it basically takes the input x that was
given to it, the n bit string that was
来判断它看起来是不是随机的。让我们
given to it, and decides whether it looks
random or it doesn't look random. Let's
看几个例子，第一个例子会用一个事实
look at a couple of examples. So the first
example basically will use the fact that
一个随机序列中，0的个数大致等于1的个数
for a random string, the number of zeros
is roughly equal to the number of ones in
换句话说，统计测试输出1。当
that string. In other words, the
statistical test is going to say one. If
且仅当序列X中0的个数减去1的个数
and only if basically the number of zeros
in the given string X minus the number of
个数不会差太多，换句话说
1's in the given string X. These numbers
are not too far apart. In other words, the
0的个数和1的个数的差别
difference between the number of 0's and
the number of 1's. Let's just say is less
是小于10倍根号n的。好，如果差别小于10倍的根号n
than ten times square root of n. Okay If
the difference is less than ten times, the
统计测试认为X序列看起来是随机的。如果
statistical test will say hey the string X looks random. If the
差别碰巧比10倍的根号n大得多
difference happens to be much bigger than
ten times square root of n, that starts to
那就看起来很可疑，测试认为你给的序列不是
look suspicious and the test,
hey the string you gave me does not
随机的，这是一个统计测试。让我们看另一个相似的例子
look random. A statistical test. Let's
look at another similar example. We'll say
在这里，统计测试说1，当且仅当
here, the statistical test will say one.
If and only if say the number of times
X序列中出现连续两个0的次数，但是我们想一想
that we have two consecutive zeros. Inside
of X. But let's think about this for a
数一数，n比特序列中，数一下
second. This basically again counts. In
this string of, n bits. It counts a number
00出现的次数。连续的两个0
of times that we see the pattern zero,
zero. Two consecutive zeros. Well for a
对一个随机序列，我们期望看到00的概率是四分之一
random string. We will expect to see 0,0
as probability one fourth. And there for
对于一个随机序列，我们期望四分之N个00。是的，四分之N的
in a random string. We'll expect about N
over four 0,0's. Yeah, N over four blocks
00。那么，统计测试会做的是，它会说，如果
a 0,0. And so, what the statistical test
will do is it will say, well, if the
00的个数近似等于四分之N，换句话说
number of zero zeros is roughly N over
four. In other words, the difference
00的个数和四分之N的差别小于10倍的根号n
between the number and N over four,
is, say, less than ten square root of n,
我们就说X看起来是随机的。如果差别比四分之N大得多
then we will say that X looks random. And
if the gap is much bigger than N over
我们就说这个序列不是随机的。然后
four, we'll say, hey, this string doesn't
really look random. And then the
统计测试就会输出0，对吧？这就是两个统计测试的例子
statistical test will output zero, okay?
So here are two examples of statistical
对于随机序列，测试会以极大概率输出1
tests that basically, for random strings,
they will output one with very high
但是对于一些序列，你懂得，那些不随机的序列，比如
probability. But for strings that, you
know, don't look random, for example,
全0序列。对于全0序列，这些测试
think of the all zero string. So the all
zero string, neither one of these tests
没有一个会输出1。并且事实上，全0序列看起来也不随机
will output, one. And in fact, the all
zero string does not look random. Let's
让我们再看一个统计测试的例子
look at one more example of the
statistical test just to kinda show you
来给大家展示统计测试能想做什么就做什么
the, basically statistical test can pretty
much do whatever they want. So here's the
这是第三个例子。我们说统计测试输出1，当且仅当
third example. Let's say that statistical
test output one if an only if I say the
最大的块，我们称之为x序列中0的最大游程
biggest blocks what we'll call this the
Maximum Run of zero inside of the string
是x序列中最长的0序列
x, this is basically the longest sequence
of zero inside of the string x. In a
在随机序列中，你希望最长0序列近似等于
random string you expect the longest
sequence of zeros to be roughly of length
log N（以2为底）。我们说如果最长0游程碰巧小于
log N. So we'll say if the longest
sequence of zero happens to be less than
10倍log N，测试就认为X序列是随机的。但是如果
ten times log N Then this test will say
that X was random. But if, all of a
突然我们看到一个0的游程比10倍log N大得多
sudden, we see a run of zeros that, say,
is much bigger than ten log N, then the
测试就认为X序列是不随机的，对吧？这是另一个
statistical test will say, the string is
not random, okay? So this is another crazy
测试做的疯狂例子。顺便说一下，大家注意到，如果你
thing that the statistical test will do.
By the way, you notice that if you give
给定这个测试一个全1序列，就是11111。测试也会
this test, the all one string. So one,
one, one, one, one. This test will also
输出1。换句话说测试认为全1序列是随机的
output one. In other words this test will
think that the all one string is random.
即便它不是，即使全1序列不是随机的
Even though it's not. Yeah, even though
one string is not particularly random.
好，统计测试不一定是对的。它们只是做它们想做的事
Okay, so statistical tests don't have to
get things right. They can do whatever
它们能测试，能判断输出是是不是随机的。你知道
they like. They can test, they can decide
to output random or not. You know, zero or
不管是0或1，类似的，这有很多其他统计测试
one, however they like. And similarly,
there are many, many, many, many other
一个人能做数百个统计测试来
statistical tests. There are literally
hundreds of statistical tests that one can
我能告诉大家在以前，你定义
think of. And I can tell you that in the
old days, basically, the way you would
某物看起来随机的方法，你会说有跟多统计测试
define. That something looks random. As
you would say, hey, here's a battery of
statistical tests. And all of them said
that this string looks random. Therefore,
所有测试说这个序列像是随机的。因此
we say that this generator that generated
the string is good generator. In other
我们认为生成这个序列的生成器很不错
words, this definition, then, uses a fixed
set of statistical tests, is actually not
换句话说，这个用很多统计测试的定义
a good definition for security, but more
generally, for crytpo. But before we talk
对更一般的密码学来说，实际上在安全方面不是一个好定义。但是在我们谈论
about actually defining security, the next
thing we talk about is how do we evaluate
安全定义之前，我们还需要讨论我们如何评估
whether a statistical test is good or not?
So to do that, we define the concept of
一个统计测试是好是坏？为此，我们定义
advantage. And so let me define the
advantage. So here we have a generator
优势的概念。那么我来定义优势的意思。我们有一个
that outputs N bit strings. And we have a
statistical tests on N bit strings. And we
输出N比特序列的生成器，我们对这N比特序列做个统计测试。
define the advantage of this generator,
as denoted by advantage sub PRG,
然后我们定义这个生成器的优势，记为优势子PRG
the advantage of the statistical test A
relative to the generator g. I'll define
统计测试A相对于生成器g的优势
it as follows, basically the difference
between two quantities. The first quantity
我会像下面这样定义它，定义为两个量之间的差距。第一个量
is basically, we ask how likely is this
statistical test to output one. When we
是统计测试输出1的概率。
give it a pseudo random string just like
here K is chosen uniformly from the C
当我们输入一个为随机序列，就比如从C空间里均匀选取的K
space we ask how likely is the statistical
test to output one when we give it a
我们考虑统计测试输出1的概率，当我们
pseudo random output generated by the
generator verses now we ask how likely is
输入有生成器产生的伪随机序列
the statistical test to output one when we
give it a truly random string. So here are
同时我们要看当我们输入真随机序列是统计测试输出1的概率
is truly random in zero random one to the
n. Okay, and yeah. We look at the
那么这里是n位真随机的01序列，好，我们来看
difference between these two quantities.
Now you realize because these are
这两个量之间的差。现在大家看到
differences of probabilities this
advantage is always going to lie in the
因为是概率的差，优势总是体现在
interval zero, one. So let's think a
little bit about what this advantage
[0,1]区间里。那么大家稍微想想这个优势意味着什么
actually means. So first of all if the
advantage happens to be close to one. Well
首先，如果优势接近1
what does that mean. That means that
somehow, the statistical test A behaves
什么意思呢？意思就是统计测试A
differently when we gave it pseudo-random
inputs, when we gave it the output of the
会有不同的结果，如果我们输入伪随机序列
generator, for when we gave it truly
random inputs, right? It somehow behaved
和生成器产生的真随机序列，对吧？
differently. In one case, it output one
with a certain probability. And in the
它表现的不用。在一种情况下，它以一定概率输出1
other case, it output one with a very
different probability, okay? So somehow,
另一种情况下，它会以完全不同的概率输出1，对吧？
it was able to behave differently. And
what they really means is that the
它就能表现地不同。这些真正想表达的是
statistical test could basically
distinguish the output of the generator
这个统计测试能将这个生成器的输出
from random. Okay, so in some sense we'll
say that this statistical test broke the
和随机序列区分开。好，在某种意义上，我们认为这个统计测试
generator G because it was able to
distinguish the output from random.
破解了生成器G，因为它能够区分输出序列和随机序列
However if the advantage is close to zero
Well what does that mean. That means that
然而这个优势和0很接近，什么意思？
basically the statistical tests behaves
pretty much the same on pseudo random
这意味着统计测试在伪随机输入
inputs. As it does on truly random inputs.
And basically there we would say that A
和真随机输入两种情况下表现一致。我们基本上可以说A
could not distinguish the generator from
random. Okay, so this sum gives you a
不能区分生成器的输出和真随机的输出。好，这个总结可以给大家
little bit of intuition about why this
concept of advantage is important. It
一点直观感受，为什么优势这一概念如此重要
basically tells us whether A was able to
break the generator, namely distinguish it
它告诉我们A是否能够破解这个生成器，即区分随机性
from random, or not able to break it. So
let's look, first of all, at a very silly
否则就不能破解它。那么我们首先再看一个很傻的例子
example. Suppose we have a statistical
test A that simply ignores its inputs and
设想我们有一个统计测试A，不管输入什么
always outputs zero. Okay. Always output
zero. What do you think of the advantage
总是输出0。好总是输出0.大家认为
of this statistical test relative to a
generator G? So, I hope everybody
这个相对于生成器G的统计测试的优势是什么？那么我希望大家
say the advantage is zero, let
me just explain, why that's the case,
都能认为优势是0，让我来解释一下为什么是这种情况
well, if the statistical test, always outputs, zero, that
如果在统计测试中总是输出0
means, pseudo random inputs, it will never
output one, so, the probability that
这意味着，输入伪随机序列是，不会输出1，所以
outputs one, is zero. Similarly, when we
give a truly random input, it still will
输出1的概率是零。相似的，当我们输入真随机序列时，它仍然
never output one, and, so, the probability
that outputs one, is zero,
不会输出1，并且输出1的概率还是0
and, so, zero minus zero is zero, so, its
advantage is zero, so, basically, and, a
所以0减0等于0，它的优势也就是0。那么
statistical test that ignores its, its
input, does not able to distinguish, truly
这个不看输入的统计测试明显不能区分
random inputs, from, a pseudo random
input, obviously. Okay, now let's look at
真随机和伪随机序列。好，我们来看
a more interesting example. So suppose we
have a generator G that satisfies a funny
一个更有趣的例子。假设我们有一个生成器G满足一个有趣的
property. It so happens that for
two-thirds of the keys The first bit
性质：有三分之二的秘钥
of the output of the generator happens to
be one, okay? So if I choose a random key
生成器输出的第一位碰巧是1，对吧？所以如果我选一个随机秘钥
with probability two-thirds, the generator
will output one as its first bit, okay? So
生成器会以三分之二的概率，第一位输出1，对吧？
that's the property of the generator that
we're looking at. Now, let's look at the
那么这就是我们看到的这个生成器的性质。现在我们来看
following statistical test. The
statistical test basically says, if the
下面的统计测试。这个测试是这样的
most signifigant bit of the string you
gave me is one, I'm gonna say one, meaning
如果这个序列的最高位是1，就输出1
I think it's random. If the most signigant
bit of the stream you gave me is not one,
我会认为它是随机的。如果输入的最高位不是1
zero, I'm gonna say zero. Okay
so now my question to you is what is the
是0，就输出0。好那么问题来了
advantage of this statistical test on the
generator G? Okay, so remember I just
对于生成器G的统计测试的优势是什么？
wrote down the definition here again. And
I'll let you think about this for a
我再在这里写一遍定义，并且大家可以想一想
second. So let me explain. Suppose we give
the statistical tests pseudo random
那么我来解释一下，假设我们对这个统计测试输入伪随机序列
inputs. By definition of G, we know that
with probability two-thirds, the first
根据G的定义，我们知道有三分之二的概率
bits in the inputs will start with the bit
one. But if it starts with a bit one, then
输入的第一位是1.但如果以1开始
the statistical test will output one. In
other words, the probability that this
那统计测试就会输出1.换句话说
statistical test outputs one is exactly
two-thirds. Now let's look at the case of
统计测试输出1的概率严格为三分之二。我们来看一下
a random string. If I give you a random
string, how likely is it that the most
随机序列的情况。如果我输入一个随机序列，
signifigant bits of the random string is
one? Well, for a random string, that
最高位是1的概率是多少？好，对于这个随机序列
happens exactly half the time, and so in
this case the statistical test will output
概率是约为一半，并且这种情况下统计测试会输出
one, with probability one-half. And so the
overall advantage is one-sixth, and
1，概率是二分之一。所以总的优势是六分之一
one-sixth is actually a non-negligible
number, that's actually a fairly large
六分之一实际上是一个不可忽略的数字，是一个相当大的
number, which basically means that this a
was able to distinguish the output. We'll
数，这意味着生成器能够区分输出了。
say that a breaks the generator G with
advantage 1/6. Okay, which basically
我们可以认为A以六分之一的优势破解了生成器G。好，
means that this generator is no good, is
broken. Okay, so now that we understand
这说明这个生成器不好，被破解了。那么我们现在理解了
what statistical tests are, we can go
ahead and define, what is a secure
统计测试是什么了，我们来更进一步定义，什么是
pseudo-random generator. So, basically, we
say that, as generator G is secure, if
一个安全伪随机生成器。那么我们说生成器G是安全的
essentially no efficient, statistical
tests can distinguish its output from
如果本质上没有有效的统计测试能区分G输出和
random. More precisely, what we'll say is
that, basically for all efficient
和随机序列。更精确地说，所有有效的
statistical tests, a... Statistical tests,
a... It so happens that if I look at the
统计测试，A..统计测试，A..如果我看
advantage. Of the statistical test E
relative to G. This advantage basically is
统计测试E对于生成器G的优势。这个优势是
negligible. So, in other words,
it's very close to zero, and as a result,
可以忽略的。换句话说，它非常接近于0，作为结果来说
this, statistical test was not able to
distinguish the output from random, and
这个统计测试不能区分生成器的输出序列和随机序列
that has to be true for all statistical
tests. So, this is a very, very pretty and
这对于所有统计测试都是对的。因此这是一个非常非常完美
elegant definition, that says that a
generator is secure, not only if a
优雅的定义，它说明了生成器是安全的，不仅
particular battery of statistical tests
says that the output looks random, but, in
一些特定的统计测试认为它的输出是随机的
fact, all efficient statistical tests will
say the output looks random. Okay? One
事实上所有有效的统计测试都认为输出是随机的，对吧？
thing I'd like to point out is, that the
restriction to efficient statistical tests
我想指出的一点是，有效统计测试的限制
is actually necessary. If we ask that all
statistical tests, regardless of whether
是必须的。如果我们考虑的所有的统计测试，不管
they're efficient or not, not be able to
distinguish the output from random. Then
是否是有效的，它们就不能够区分生成器的输出序列和随机序列了。
in fact, that can not be satisfied. So in
other words if we took out the
事实上，这是无法被满足的。换句话说，如果我们
requirements that the test be efficient.
Then this definition would be
去掉测试是有效的要求，那么这个定义
unsatisfiable. And I'll leave this as a
simple puzzle for you to think about. But
无法被满足。我把这点留给大家当做一个小问题思考一下
basically the fact is that restricting
this definition into only efficient
但是实际上限制定义在有效的
statistical tests is actually necessary
for this to be satisfiable. So now that we
统计测试范围内是必要的，这样定义才能被满足
have a definition, the next question is
can we actually construct a generator and
现在我们有了这个定义，下一个问题就是我们能否构造一个生成器
then prove that it is in fact a secure
PRG. In other words, prove that no
并且证明它实际上是安全的PRG。换句话说，就是证明
efficient statistical test can distinguish
its output from random. And it turns out
没有有效的统计测试能区分生成器的输出序列和随机序列。
that the answer is we actually can't. In
fact, it's not known. If there are any
结果答案就是我们不能，实际上不知道是否
probably secure PRG's. Then I will just
say very briefly the reason is that if you
有任何可能的安全PRG。我来说一个简单的理由
could prove that a particular generator is
secure that would actually imply that P
如果你能证明一个特定的生成器是安全的，那意味着
is not equal to NP. And I don't want to
dwell on this. Because I don't want to
P不等于NP。我不想在这个地方纠结。因为我不想
assume that you guys know what P and NP
are. But I'll tell you as a simple fact
假定大家都知道P和NP是什么。但我会简单告诉大家
that in fact in P is equal to NP. Then
it's very easy to show that there are no
事实是P是等于NP的。显而易见没有
secure PRGs. And so if you could prove to
me that a particular PRG is secure, that
安全的PRG。如果大家能够证明给我看看一个特定的PRG是安全的
would imply that P is not equal to
NP. Again, I will leave this to
那意味着P不等于NP。我会把这个
you as a simple puzzle to think about.
But, even though we can't actually
再当做一个问题留给大家思考。但是尽管我们实际上不能
rigorously prove that a particular PRG is
secure, we still have lots and lots and
严格证明一个特定的PRG是安全的，我们任然有很多
lots of heuristic candidates, and we even
saw some of those in the previous
候选方案，我们之前甚至看到过一些
segments. Okay now that we understand what
is a secure PRG. I want to talk a little
好，现在我们理解了什么是一个安全的PRG。我想稍微讨论一下
bit about some applications and
implications of this definition. And so
这个定义的一些应用以及含义。那么
the first thing I want to show you is that
in fact a secure PRG is necessarily
我想给大家看的第一件事实际上是一个安全的PRG
unpredictable. In a previous segment, we
talked about what it means for a generator
是不可预测的。在前面一节，我们讨论了一个生成器
to be unpredictable. And we said that,
basically, what that means is that, given
不可预测是什么意思。我们说，这个意思是
a prefix of the output generator, it's
impossible to predict the next bit of the
给定生成器输出的前一部分，我们不能预测下一位输出
output. Okay, so we'd like to show that if
a generator is secure, then necessarily,
好，我们想要表明一个生成器是否安全，必须
it means it's unpredictable. And so the
only way we're gonna do that is using the
意味着它是不可预测的。唯一的方式就是使用
contrapositive. That is, we're gonna say
that if you give me a generator that is
逆否命题。也就是说，如果你给出一个可预测的生成器
predictable, then necessarily, it's
insecure. In other words, necessarily, I
那么它是不安全的。换句话说
can distinguish it from random. And so
let's see, this is actually a very simple
我能区分生成器的输出和随机序列的输出。我们来看看，这是一个简单的
fact. And so let's see how we would do
that. So suppose you give me a predictor.
事实。我们看看我们怎么用这个事实。假定你给出一个预测
In other words, suppose you give me an
efficient algorithm, such that, in fact,
换句话说，假定你给出一个有效的算法，像这样，事实上
if I give this algorithm the output of the
generator, but I give it only the first
如果我把生成器的输出作为算法的输入，但我只输入
I-bits of the outputs. It's able to
predict the next bit of the output. In
输出序列的前I比特。它能够预测下一比特的输出。
other words given the first I-bit it's
able to predict the I plus first bit. And
换句话说，给定的前I比特能够预测I+1位
it does that with a certain probability.
So let's say if we choose a random k. From
该算法能够以一定概率实现。因此我们说如果我们从秘钥空间选择一个随机的k
the keyspace. Then, clearly, a done predictor would be able to predict the
然后预测机就能够
next bit with probability one-half, simply
just guess the bits. You'll be right with
以一半的概率预测下一位。简单地猜下这些比特，你能
probability one-half. However, this
algorithm A is able to predict the next
有一半的概率正确。然而算法A也能够
bit with probability half with epsilon. So
it's bound to the way. From a half. And,
一以二分之一加epsilon的概率预测下一位。因此它是被这样界定的。
in fact, we require that this by true for
some non negligible epsilon. So, for
实际上，我们要求这对某些不能忽略的epsilon成立
example, epsilon =1/1000 would already be a
dangerous predictor, because it can
比如，epsilon=1/1000，这会是一个危险的预测机，因为它能
predict the next bits, given a prefix,
with non negligible advantage. Okay, so
在给定前缀时，以不可忽略的优势预测下一位
suppose we have such an algorithm. Let's
see that we can use this algorithm to
假定我们有这样一个算法，我们来看我们能用这个算法
break our generator. In other words to
show that a generator is distinguishable
来破解我们的生成器。换句话说，是为了表明一个生成器是和
from random and therefore, is insecure. So
what we'll do is we'll define a
随机序列可以区分的，因此是不安全的。那么我们要做的是定义
statistical test. So, let's define the
statistical test B as follows. Basically,
一个统计测试。我们按如下方式定义统计测试B
B, given a string, x, what it will do, is
it will simply run algorithm A on the
B，给定序列x，接下来要做的是
first I-bit of the string x that it was
given. And, statistical test b is simply
对给定的x序列前i比特使用算法A。统计测试B简单地
gonna ask, was a successful in predicting
the I-plus first bit of the string? If it
问一下，是否成功地预测了第i+1位？
was successful, then it's gonna output
one. And if it wasn't successful, then
如果是成功的，它就会输出1.如果不成功
it's gonna output zero. Okay. This our
statistical task. Let's put it in a box So
就会输出0。好，这就是我们的统计任务。我们把它一个盒子中
we can take it wherever we like. And we
can run the statistical test on any N bit
我们能随意的使用。并且我们能用任意N比特
string that's given to us as inputs. So
now, let's look at what happens. Suppose
序列作为输入运行统计测试。现在我们来看看发生了什么。假定
we give the statistical test, a truly
random string. So a truly random string R.
我们在统计测试中输入真随机序列，R
And we ask, what is the probability that
the statistical test outputs one? Well,
我们想知道会有多大概率输出1？
for a truly random string, the I+1
bit is totally independent of the first
对于一个真随机序列，第i+1是独立于
I-bits. So whatever this algorithm is
gonna output is completely independent of
前I比特的。所以算法A的输出也是完全独立于
what's, I+1 bit of the string R is.
And so whatever A outputs the probability
序列R的i+1位的，所以不管A输出什么，概率
is going to be equal to some random bit X I+1. Random independent bit X I+1, that
都是等于随机的第i+1位，与第i+1位独立
probability is exactly 1/2. In other
words, algorithm a simply has no
概率为1/2.换句话说，算法A不提供第i+1位的任何信息
information about what the bit X I+1 is, and so necessarily, the probability is
第I+1位的任何信息。并且
able to predict X I+1 is exactly one half. On the other hand, let's look at
能够预测第I+1位是什么的概率为1/2.另一方面，我们来看
what happens when we give our statistical
tests a pseudo-random sequence, okay. So
当我们在统计测试输入伪随机序列会发生什么
now we're going to run the statistical
test on the output of the generator, and
好，我们对生成器的输出进行统计测试
we ask how likely is it to output one.
Well, by definition of A, we know that
我们想知道输出1的可能多大。根据定义A，我们知道
when we give it the first I bits of the
output of the generator, it's able to
当我们把生成器的前I位作为输入时，它能
predict the next bit with probability 1/2 + epislon. So in this case our
以1/2+epislon的概率预测。因此这种情况下
statistical test B will output one with
probability greater than 1/2 + epsilon
统计测试B会以大于1/2+epislon的概率输出1
And basically what this means, is if we look at the advantage of our
这就意味着如果我们看
statistical tests over the generator G
it's basically, the difference between
统计测试对于生成器G的优势，就是
this quantity and that quantity. There's a
difference between the two. You can see
两个量间的差别。你能够看出来两者的差
that it's clearly greater than an epsilon.
So what this means is that if algorithm A
是大于epsilon的。这意味着如果算法A
is able to predict the next bits with
advantage epsilon, then algorithm B is
能够以epsilon的优势预测下一位，那么算法B
able to distinguish the output of the
generator with advantage epsilon. Okay? So
能够以epsilon的优势区分生成器的输出，对吧？
if A is a good predictor, B is a good
statistical test that break the generator.
那么如果A是一个好的预测机，B是一个破解了生成器的好统计测试
And as we said, the counter-positive of
that is that if G is a secure generator,
就如我们说的，这个逆否命题是如果生成器G安全
then there are no good statistical tests.
And as a result, there are no predictors.
那么就没有好的统计测试，同样，也没有好的预测机
Okay? Which means that the generator is,
as we said, unpredictable. Okay, so, so
对吧？意思就是我们所说的生成器是不可预测的。好，目前为止
far, what we've seen is that if the
generator is secure, necessarily, it's
我们看到的是如果生成器是安全的
impossible to predict the I+1 bit,
given first I bits.
就不可能在给定前I比特时预测第I+1比特。
Now there's a very elegant and remarkable
theorem Yao back in 1982. They
1982年，姚期智给出了一个优雅非凡的定理
chose it, in fact the converse is also
true. In other words, if I give you a
人们认同了这个定理。实际上逆命题也是成立的。换句话说，如果我给出
generator that's unpredictable, so you
cannot predict the I+1 bits from the
一个不可预测的生成器，那么你就不能根据前I位预测第I+1位
first I bits, and that's true for all I.
That generator, in fact, is secure. Okay,
I取任何值都成立。事实上这个生成器是安全的。好
so let me state the theorem a little bit
more precicely. So here we have our
我来吧这个定理阐述的更清楚点。我们使
generator that outputs n bit outputs. The
theorem says the following, basically for
生成器输出n比特，定理告诉我们
all bit positions, it's impossible to
predict I+1 bit of the output
对所有比特位，都不可能根据前I位预测第I+1位输出
given the first I bit. And that's true for
all I. In other words, again, the
这对于所有I均成立。换句话说
generator is unpredictable for all bit
positions. Then, that, in fact, implies
生成器对于任何比特位都无法预测。事实上这就意味着
that the generator is a secure PRG.
I want paraphrase this in English,
生成器是一个安全的PRG。我想用英语解释这个
and so the way to kinda interpret this
result is to say that it's basically these
并且组织下语言，这个结果就是这些
next bit predictors. These predictors that
try to predict the I+1 bit given the
下一位预测机能够在给定前I位是预测第I+1位
first I bits. If they're not able to
distinguish G from random, then, in fact,
如果他们不能区分G的输出和随机序列的输出，那么事实上
no statistical test is going to
distinguish G from random. So kind of next
就没有统计测试能区分了。这些
bit predictors are in some sense
universal, predictors, when it comes to
下一位预测机某种意义上是指普遍的预测机。当说到
distinguishing things from random. This
theorem, by the way, it's not too
区分随机性时，顺便说下，这个定理，不难
difficult to prove, but there's a very
elegant idea behind its proof. I'm not
证明，但是在这个证明背后有一个非常优雅的想法。
gonna do the proof here, but I encourage
you to think about this as a puzzle, try
在这里我不做证明，但是我鼓励大家把它当做一个问题思考
to kind of try to prove this theorem
yourself. Let me show you kind of one cute
尝试自己证明它。我来给大家展示一个定理稍微
implication of this theorem. So let me ask
you the following question. Suppose I give
有趣的影响。我要问大家下面几个问题，假定我给出
you a generator and I tell you that given
the last bit of the output. It's easy to
一个生成器，并且我告诉大家给定的输出的最后一位
predict the first bit of the outputs,
okay? So given the last end bits, you can
很容易就能预测输出的第一位，对吧？那么给定最后一位，你可以
compute the first end bits. That's kind of
the opposite of predictability, right?
第一位，这和预测正好相反，对吧？
Predictability mean given the first
bit, you can produce the next bits. Here,
可预测性指的是给定第一位，你能得到下一位。这里
given the last bits, you can produce the
first ones. And my question to you, does
给定最后一位，你能得到第一位。那么我的问题是
that mean that the generator is
predictable? Can you somehow, from this
这意味着生成器是可预测的吗？能否根据这个
fact, still build a predictor for this
generator? This is kind of a simple
事实为生成器构造一个预测机呢？这是一个
application of Yao theorem let me explain to
you the answer is actually yes let me
姚期智定理的简单应用。我来给大家解释一下这个问题的答案是yes
explain why how do we build this generator
well, actually we're not going to build it
我解释一下怎样构造这个生成器，实际上我们不需要构造它
I'm going to show you that the generator
exists. Well because an over two bits
我会证明给大家这个生成器是存在的，就是因为超过两字节
first an over two bits doesn't necessarily
mean that the generator here let me write
首先超过两字节并不意味着生成器，我这样写
them this way what it means is that g is
not secure. Because just as we did before
即G不安全。因为如之前所说
it's very easy to build a statistical test
that will distinguish the output of G from
容易构造一个统计测试来区分G的输出和
uniform. So G is not secure. But if G Is not
secure, by Yao's Theorem, that means that
均匀分布序列。但如果G不安全，根据姚定理，那就是指
G is predectible. So in other words, there
exists some I for which given the first I
G是可预测的。因此换句话说，存在某个I，给定输出前I位
bits of the output, you can build the I+1 bits of the output. Okay, so
你能构造第I+1位的输出。好
even though I can't quite point to you a
predicter, we know that a predicter must
即使我不能为大家构造预测算法，但我们知道预测算法一定存在
exist. So that's a one cute simple
application of Yao theorem. Now before we
那么这就是姚定理的一个简单应用。现在在我们
end the segment I want to kind of,
generalize a little bit of what we did.
结束这个部分之前，我想对我们所做的进行一个推广
And introduce a little bit of important
notation that's going to be useful
那就引入一些一直都很有用的重要符号
actually throughout. So, we're gonna
generalize the concept of
我们来推广
indistinguishability from uniform, to
indistinguishability of two general
与均匀分布不可区分的概念，到两个一般分布间的不可区分
distributions. So, suppose I give you p1
and p2, and we ask, can these two
设想我给出p1和p2，那么我们想知道这两个
distributions be distinguished? And so
we'll say that the distributions are
分布可区分吗？我们说这些分布
computationally indistinguishable, and
we'll denote this by p1, a squiggly p. P2.
计算上不可区分的，我们记为p1，约等于p,p2
This means that, in polynomial time, P1
cannot be distinguished from P2. And we'll
这意味着，在多项式时间里，p1和p2无法区分
say that they're indistinguishable,
basically, just as before
我们说他们是不可区分的，与之前一样
if basically for all, efficient, statistical
tests, statistical tests. A it so happens
对所有有效的统计测试A
that if I sample from the distribution P1.
And I give the output to A. Versus if I
如果我从分布p1里取样，并且把输出给A。作为对比
sample from the distribution P2, and I
give the sample to A. Then basically A
若果我从p2中取样，也交给A。那么基本上A对
behaves the same in both cases. In
another-wards the difference between these
两种情况表现一致。换句话说，这
two probabilities is negligible. And this
has to be true for all statistical tests.
两概率的差是可以忽略的。这对所有统计测试都成立
For all efficient statistical tests. Okay?
So if this is the case then we say that,
对所有的统计测试，对吧？如果是这种情况，我们说
well A couldn't distinguish it's advantage
in distinguishing two distributions is
A不能区分两个分布时，这两个分布的优势
negligible and if that's true for all
efficient statistical tests then we say
是可以忽略的。如果这对所有有效的统计测试都成立
that the distributions are basically
computationaly indistinguishable,
我们就说这些分布在计算上无法区分
because an efficient algorithm cannot
distinguish them. And just to show you how
因为一个有效的算法都不能区分它们。我是为了告诉大家
useful this notation is, basically using
this notation the definition of security
这个符号很有用，我们可以用它表示安全PRG的定义
for PRG just says. That if I give you a
pseudo-random distribution. In other
如果我给出一个伪随机分布，换句话说
words, I choose K at random, and that
outputs a G of K. That distribution is
随机地选取K，然后输出相应的G。这个分布
computationally indistinguishable from the
uniform distribution. So you can see this,
和均匀分布在计算上是不可区分的。因此大家也看到了
this very simple notation captures the
whole definition of pseudo-random
这个非常简单的符号表达了伪随机生成器的整个定义
generators. Okay, so we're gonna make use
of this notation. In the next segment,
好，我们后面会用到这个符号。在下一节中
when we define, what does it mean for a
cipher to be secure.
当我们定义密码时，它就代表安全